Sarah E. Ellis Collection 019
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Sarah E. Ellis Papers
1945-1979
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Ellis, Sarah E.
019
1.5 Linear feet
3 Boxes
Arrangement
Processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
Sarah Ellis became a citizen activist when in 1959 urban renewal caused the forced relocation of Cy Ellis Raw Bar from the Municipal Fish Market Building on the Southwest Waterfront. Sarah's husband Cy Ellis died of a heart attack in November 1959 and Mrs. Ellis was forced to relocate the restaurant in December 1959. The restaurant was forced to move again from E Street NW when construction on the new Metro subway began in the 1960s. Mrs. Ellis' ten-year fight in the courts and Congress helped establish the Priority Law which requires that long-established businesses can use the "grandfather" clause to avoid relocation in urban renewal areas. Mrs. Ellis moved her restaurant back to the redeveloped Southwest waterfront in 1970. Born on a Potomac River farm in St. Mary's County, Maryland, Sarah married Cy Ellis and moved to Washington, D.C. sometime after World War I to open an oyster bar restaurant.
Custodial History
Donor unknown.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, clippings, meeting minutes, reports, and pamphlets of local issues and citizens' organizations in which Mrs. Ellis was involved; including the Chillum Heights Citizens' Association, the D.C. Federation of Citizens' Associations, Junior Village, the Committee for the Rights of the D.C. Business Community, urban renewal, home rule, and mass transit. Of significance, is a 1972 report titled "Report of the Special Citizens' Advisory Committee on Urban Renewal in D.C."
Neighborhoods; Citizens' Associations; Urban renewal; Restaurateurs; Southwest (Washington, D.C.); Takoma Park (Washington, D.C.); Correspondence; Minutes (Records); Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc)
- Series 1
  - Minutes Chillum Heights Citizens Association and correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chillum Heights Citizens Association Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Federation of Citizens Associations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee for the Rights of the Washington D.C. Business Community, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bill Announcements and other Congressional Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and Other materials, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous letters and testimony by Mrs. Ellis, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Historic Landmarks and districts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Urban renewal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Urban renewal and home rule, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Potomac River, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Metro and mass transit, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous inspirational notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Downtown redevelopment and urban renewal, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History and bicentennial activities, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reports, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Southwest Spectator Article re Mrs. Ellis, 26041 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Capitol Hill Spectator - SW Waterfront Festival, 23874 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rolled Petition in support of Municipal Fish Market, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Test of Roosevelt Speech given to Mrs. Ellis by Fund, 13486 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Junior Village, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Junior Village, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Junior Village, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Junior Village, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Junior Village, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Junior Village - clippings, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)